ladies and gentlemen if you clicked on
this video I've got a very simple
message for you every single one of you
should try to be as strong as possible
at the game of chess and the reason for
that is very simple absolutely every
other person that you interact with will
respect you much more every other person
that you interact with will think that
you are an intellectual a sophisticated
form of human being now not that is
Justified but the game of chess is
falsely associated with intelligence and
the lowest form of this intelligence or
capability is 100 ELO the lowest
possible form of chest strength that a
person can
have and in today's video I will show
you a chess game played between two
individuals in the ELO range of
100 but one
caveat we all have to start somewhere
all of us have started Chess at some
point at a certain location on the
rating
scale this is a new subscriber by the
name of Joe everybody say hi Joe he
didn't hear you because that's not the
way the internet works but Joe will
definitely get a warm big welcome on
this channel what we do on this channel
what we do in this playlist called how
to lose a chess is we break games down
and the point is that we're not laughing
at Joe or his
opponent we are looking at a mirror
image reflection of ourselves see chz
has this way of exposing all of our
flaws of exposing our of exposing our
hubris our arrogance our lack of empathy
for other people we all need to look at
the mirror and remember get as strong as
possible in chess because everybody will
think more highly of you shout out to
Joe for being brave enough to submit
this game let's break it down it is
187 versus 166 and Joe's opponent from
Austria named 16t has like a as a like a
James Bond name he just the name is just
is James Bond here we go Joe begins with
E4 already a very good move we don't
have to wait long to get the action bang
in here 16t responds with Pawn to
F5 a very strong move all right Joe
plays
D3 that's fine you know he spent a
little bit of time on that move D3 is an
okay move this is called the duras
Gambit I'm not sure that black knew that
I think black just was learning how to
move the pawns Joe plays D3 nice and
defensive he could have taken on F5 and
if he had taken on F5 the diagonal to
the king would have been wide open so
you've got to be very careful already as
black it's like very close to being
Checkmate so Joe plays defensively black
plays Pawn takes Pawn takes and is
immediately lost it took three moves you
know chest is hard but one thing you
will learn as a beginner is how not to
poop your pants within the first 10
moves this is very very important I
teach it in my book and today's video is
in fact
sponsored buy my book it's back there
how to win a chess it'll teach you
everything to not get this type of
position in the first three moves the
reason this is so bad is because now
this check is completely lethal and you
should always look for checks uh because
sometimes they're really good Queen H5
just wins the game black goes here Queen
E5 Bishop C4 and there's Checkmate on
the horizon here's Checkmate right away
uh but also there is G6 Queen E5 and you
would simply pick up a rook so you need
to always be able to look for checks
it's why you don't want to open up your
king early in the game but Joe is a
principal man plays Knight F3 developing
his Knight like he knows he should
Knight F6 develops both Knights Knights
before Bishops I love this by Mr Joseph
what an absolute Beast playing like a
Grandmaster to true to his name and now
black of course should Mirror Image
develop your Knights first but instead
black very active throws yet another
Pawn into the center of the board this
is simply a counting mistake all
beginners watching this can improve this
one skill counting is the skill in chess
when you count the amount of pieces that
can capture on a square or a piece right
square or a piece so this is one and
there's zero for black so that's why
black should have went D6 or this gotten
a piece to look at another piece another
good way to improve a chess think of
your pieces as having eyeballs Vision
all right this sees that this sees that
and this sees that so it is not a good
trade but damn it Joseph is a man of
principle and in the opening we tell
beginners not to make multiple moves
with pieces that they've already gotten
out so he moves his Bishop
he moves his Bishop cuz he knows he's
supposed to develop his pieces all right
unfortunately what it does for black is
that it leaves black with two Center
pawns and now black captures on e4 now
every time a pawn moves in chess or any
piece you got to think about what opens
up what things now see things they
didn't see before the queen has Vision
across the board you could go take take
Knight takes and threaten a fork but
instead of that sadly Joe here falls for
the common beginner mistake of having
tunnel vision and he takes the Pawn that
just landed on that square yet again a
counting mistake black has two things
that can see that pawn you only have one
and so after d takes E4 Knight takes E4
Joe realizes uhoh I just lost the
Knight and that is very common that is a
beginner mistake that is quite avoidable
and hopefully does not happen again he
saw the pawn he took it back and he went
damn it I lost my knight but now he
castles and now black finds a really
nice tactical idea here considering that
black just moved the night black
completely forgets that they have any
other pieces and they continue to move
the Knight forward losing it in one move
completely that move hangs a knight that
no questions asked so this is one thing
you should avoid as a beginner you
should avoid moving a piece and then
thinking you have to move it again that
is literally not the law at all I don't
know why you all think that way you have
other pieces and you've got to viol you
got to stop violating principles Knight
C3 played now this is a bad move
because you can just be taken joo's here
though I I don't really I don't
understand I I don't it it's standing on
the same line as the Queen the Knight
can now take the bishop black here
because they are up a knight because
they took the Knight should trade pieces
they they should trade the queen they
should trade the bishop and then they
got to get the king to safety because in
chess you need material and King safety
and you need to stop playing chess like
it's Russian Roulette I mean you're
basically like spinning the chest pieces
around and maybe some of them will fall
off the table black here plays a move
that's so high level I can't even begin
to understand it white moves the queen
to attack the Knight that could have
been taken black plays Bishop
B4 defending the knight from the queen
taking it but not from the pawn the pawn
can still absolutely take and Joe clutch
as ever does in fact find that move and
now that Bishop is hanging as
well so black moves the bishop all the
way to the home
Square why why not literally any other
Square literally any other Square was
better why would you put the pieces all
on the back rank now this position my
man Joe plays the powerful Rook to D1
and I think his idea was to take the
queen he kind of forgot the queen could
take him too friends enemies your queen
can't attack a queen that's not how that
works the cuz the queen could take you
you can't beat up yourself I mean I
guess you don't though all right Bishop
D7 powerful move uh White is now totally
winning that's mostly because the Knight
can take the pawn and the king is still
in the center uh but joo's here you know
what I don't hate this move 40 seconds
spent on this move maybe he was getting
the delivery food at the front door that
move attacks that pawn uh now two things
attack that pawn and The Rook pins the
bishop to the queen none of them know
any of that but yeah I'm just telling
you black goes here I love that
excellent excellent development now if
only the bishop was there you know if
only this was the position black would
be fine I mean black would be completely
lost but for 100 black is fine anyway
Queen E3 moves out of the way to attack
the pawn the pawn is now defended and
now rather than taking it Joe attacks it
yet again he really really wants to make
sure he can win this Pawn before he
takes it he's a meticulous guy you know
what they say uh measured twice caught
once or something I think that's what
they say in this position uh 16t plays
Bishop D6 which he could have played
here but but didn't all right but but
didn't I shouldn't say he by the way I
don't even know all right there's my see
that's that that's that subconscious you
know 90% 85% male audience I'm by the
way this channel is up to about 9010 at
the beginning of the chess boom I had
99% male audience which was wild that is
wild you you you lunatics and now now
it's like 891 now it's like 9010 so it's
gotten 10x bigger so uh Rook B5 all
right Rook B5 powerful move here here
attacks and threatens the pawn on B7 and
black plays the most logical move thus
far B6 pushing the pawn forward it is
defended three times one two three and
look at Joe look at this positional move
by Joe Queen up to E4 the idea of this
move is to put pressure on the Knight
that was just weakened with the pawn
moving up you see Joe didn't want to
attack the Knight the Knight was
defended very well so he goes here and
now here this is excellent 187 ELO chess
excellent stuff plays A6 attacking The
Rook Rook goes back to D5 and now my man
Joe plays Bishop to G5 by the way I
think black here thought he was castling
I said I did it again black thought that
uh they were castling but instead they
moved the Rook to f8 or they just don't
know about castling but white did it so
they should do it too Joe plays Bishop
to G5 black plays Bishop to
E7 strong move defending yourself it's
again a completely lost position because
Black's completely stuck in the center
so the the winning idea here for white
is literally to rip open the position
and after Knight E5 Rook E5 you just
this is not a defendable position you
will take this you will take this it's
it's over but they don't know that
because they don't have the patterns yet
they they don't have it all Bishop B7
nowo plays Rook D1 which by the way is a
top computer move Rook D1 this is called
a battery onto the bishop if white were
to take they would get a bishop and a
queen they would get a bishop and black
would get both Rooks you do the math
Queen and Bishop is 12 two Rooks is 10
Queen and Bishop are always better um
black plays Bishop takes Bishop which is
a good move white plays Knight takes
Bishop because when you're 187 you
discover new things about the position
every single turn Queen takes G5 and at
this point Joe's 187 brain kicked in and
went there's a queen there which means
my king is in danger so I need to go
here no actually no no you don't none of
that even began to I don't even what's
the queen doing the first thing we got
to ask ourselves is can the queen take
anything it can but then I take back so
no need to go here can do I have a check
in this position yeah bad bad bad can I
take anything yeah free Bishop now you
got to realize you know you got back up
but Joe plays here safe safe move by Joe
and now black puts the queen back on the
home Square again black loves moving
pieces out and then moving them back to
the home Square I don't know what what
Black's purpose is but black moves the
queen out and a move later goes back to
the home SC now this move is still
completely crushing it is the best move
this is even better because you get to
the king and and Joe plays F4 not a bad
move at all don't hate that move you
can't take I don't know if Joe saw that
but he's he's PP on the pp here put
pressure on the pin piece now black here
plays a very powerful move Knight to D4
which hangs the Knight to the same Pawn
also it removes the defense of the E5
Pawn so now Rook E5 is completely
devastating
but Joe is a simple man and he see check
he play check it's a check you never
know what could happen right black has
to block block or move the king black
plays Rook F7 okay I mean you know at
least black didn't move the king a lot
of people think I'm in check I got to
move the king Black Blocks with the Rook
all right now Joe obviously takes the
Rook with the
bishop you know what Joe you're on to
something you took a pawn with Sheck now
you could take a knight you could take
the Rook you could also play Queen H7
Queen h8 is mate all right now we now
all right we took the Knight bless no
problem now Black Blocks it's still a
game in fact white is only a pawn up I
mean really this is this is very
complicated stuff Bishop goes back to E2
all right White's got a very powerful
position strong pressure here Bishop is
rotating around this way now black plays
the very mysterious Queen to B8 17
seconds spent on that move I would love
to get into the brain of a 166 and see
what neurons are firing for a move like
Queen to B8 to be played because it does
nothing but why did they play Queen B I
don't know fascinating stuff now Joe
plays F5 he's trying to attack the king
he doesn't realize again counting
exercise black controls that three times
but white is still in very good shape
because these pieces are out of the game
14 pieces of material are outside of the
battle just having a cigarette all right
Pawn takes
F5 all right and and now and now
unfortunately unfortunately 187 brain
kicks in white plays Rook takes F5 so
Joe's idea was to trade he
miscounts and luckily he doesn't go all
in sometimes as a beginner you just take
everything Joe resets and plays Queen E5
and you'll notice Joe here spent 18
seconds probably questioning why he ever
downloaded the chess.com app and now he
is down a full Rook but he still has
attacking possibilities the bishop could
still come here The Rook still has to
come here you got to set what's called a
mating net you got to make sure the king
can't escape over there uh black here
plays The Very powerful Bishop takes C2
winning yet another Pawn black now up
Five Points of material white plays Rook
D2 saving his rook and black again moves
the bishop he couldn't move it back to
the home Square Bishop
F5 and now I got to give credit where
it's zo because Joe never let up Joe in
this position could have just fallen
over and said you know what I'm going to
lose no Joe attacks G four and if we
know anything about our protagonist with
the black pieces they are going to move
the bishop to the
homes very close close but no cigar did
not move the bishop to the home square
but moved it very very close now if
you're playing white here you got to do
this but Joe a man of principle a man of
tunnel vision G4 H4 here we go and now
officially you are completely lost you
are completely lost here because black
should move the queen and trade Queens
white has no danger to the black
position with no Queen the queen is a
very powerful
piece instead of that black plays Rook
G7 now white is winning very close
Bishop C4 Rook F2 black has to find only
moves to survive Bishop C4 swarms the
king but with his Pawn threatened Joe
plays G5 five and black is yet again
winning if he brings his Queen to help
black plays H6 trying to fight back and
yet again Joe has to activate his bishop
and his Rook he's refusing to do so he's
not he finds Bishop C4 20 seconds spent
on this move absolutely clutch find Rook
F2 is basically mate the black king
completely stranded in the open H takes
G5 and Joe does not tunnel vision he
does not take back he plays Rook F2
Rook F2 check he's found it oh my
goodness the
187 and black can only block the check
until he is mated the King has no legal
moves and this is a lesson for why you
should not hide your queen in the corner
of the board in a bunker black plays
Rook F7 and the game is over Joe finds
Rook F7 King G8 and
queen okay Queen G7 was made Rook D7 won
a bishop and then was made Rook
G7 okay and now Joe plays Rook G6 all
right he could have taken the bishop
Rook G6 discovered check the only move
is King H7 and now Joe ends the game
with
Queen
okay okay um that's still made next
move there's an m in the evaluation
black literally cannot get out of
checkmate at all and what black should
be doing now is getting the queen in to
help black goes
here the idea I guess was to play
peekaboo that was the idea and then
you're G to go here you're gonna go
peekaboo and you're going to see all
this queen G queen queen G7 is mate Joe
doesn't find it Joe Joe respects the
threat of the queen and plays D5 he
blocks the Queen's Vision but this is
still made now Black's best hope here is
to get the rook in the game and he does
and now Queen G7 is no longer possible
possible instead you have to find that
check that check that check or one of
those checks you can't move your Rook
cuz you're pinned Joe clutch again finds
Bishop D3 check Black's only king move
is now moving up and queen F6 leads to
mate Rook G8 leads to mate in a few
moves and you win the rook and in this
position finally Joe finds Rook
to Rook takes G6
Bishop takes King
takes and Joe is
down a
bishop Queen and Bishop versus
queen he had so many chances and
unfortunately he found none of them this
is why we always have to practice
checkmates as a beginner you got to
drill mates in One you have to be a
killer at finding mateson one and then
you have to move on to mateson two all
right but instead of that Joe doesn't
find it Joe goes here pressure on the
clock he probably felt the nerves and
now he is
unfortunately going to lose this
game but then Joe saw a
light and in this position despite
having a Checkmate in one about 17
times Joe got a second Breath of Life he
played H5
and in this position Black's Queen is
stuck so black needs to bring the queen
around like a car that's parked in a
parking lot trade the Queens stop
White's Pawn Win the end game with their
pawns but black is rated
166 and after H5 is played for an
inexplicable reason black moves the king
back one square to f8 that move doesn't
even even begin to make sense doesn't
begin to make sense because if you have
these powerful pieces and you're not in
check you shouldn't move your king I
guess black thought this was a bishop
black goes here Joe continues pushing
and suddenly Joe goes from losing to
equal to winning because there is no way
for black to stop the pawns
geometrically the King goes to F7 and
now without even knowing it Joseph the
new subscriber to the channel played the
best computer move he just played H5 and
H6 what looks like the most natural move
in this position H7 but H7 loses a major
chunk of the advantage because the queen
can stop the pawn and if you go here
trying to get it through you might win
but if you make the wrong move black
survives so instead of that after
playing H5 and H6 Joseph played the move
Queen to G7 using his Pawn as an anchor
for his Queen Queen the black king
completely stuck he has to move to the
back rank Pawn to H7 and Joe made a
Monumental comeback in this game Queen
takes D5 he promoted a pawn and he
latter checkmated his opponent with his
two freshly mined
queens that was a
game between two 100 rated players I got
news for you 100 ELO is Elo hell because
these guys were not even that bad sure
Joe had 16 misses sure sure their
accuracy was 33.1 and
27.0 but
honestly that game was pretty
competitive both white and black missed
some chances in the opening the middle
game battle was fairly even White's
endgame Precision Was A Cut Above off
black there you
go shout out to Joe and shout out to
every new member of the Chess World we
all have to start somewhere and Joe is
already up to 350
rapid
so get out of here